I'm really sorry that I can't go
cheer you on today.
I did put in a request
to take the day off, you know.
Hey, that's totally fine.
It's not fine with me.
I mean, that expulsion geezer
will be judging, right?
I was hoping to give him
a piece of my mind.
Definitely don't come, please!
Hey, I'm just kidding.
I'm messing with you!
Well, you don't sound like you're kidding.
Hey. You're nervous, aren't you?
Nope! Not at all!
Oh, yes you are.
I mean, your face is a little strained.
Like, "No matter what, I'm gonna win!"
You know?
Oh, leave me alone. Is that wrong?
Not at all.
Actually, why wouldn't you feel that way?
It's all about winning!
You go out there and let them have it!
Not that I need you to tell me that.
Yeah, yeah, is that right?
- Hey, Mom.
- Hm?
Why did you name me...
- Akane?
- Huh?
EIGHTH STORY
WHAT THEY WANT
STUDENT RAKUGO COMPETITION - KARAKU CUP
PERFORMANCES WILL BEGIN SOON
I'm telling you, you're gonna win!
You'll crush it!
Uh, yeah. I guess so.
- Wait, so much small change...
- Make me look cute!
What's wrong, Shohei?
Why are you so freaked out?
W-Well, this is my first ever final!
I never thought I'd make it this far.
Well, your tension
is pointless, all right?
You don't stand a chance
of winning, anyway.
Just make some nice memories
before you leave!
Hey, shut up! I know that, okay?
It's not like you have it in the bag
this time either, Karashi.
There's a professional voice actress here,
and don't forget about that
high school girl from yesterday.
Huh? High school girl?
Are you actually serious?
You watched all the performances,
didn't you?
I have no clue how much talent she has,
but anyone who bails on winning
from the start is no rival of mine anyway.
AKANE - JUGEMU
Wow, this place is heating up like crazy.
Partly because it's the final, I guess,
but it's got that fire that's
unique to student--
Guriko.
What are these?
What do you mean? They're our disguises!
If Master Issho finds out
Shiguma's apprentices are here,
there'll be hell to pay!
Not to mention, today is...
Look, you don't think we'd stand out even
more in these get-ups?
How stupid are you?
In the first place,
what kind of fashion is this?
Oh, uh... I-I'm sorry.
- Why are you dressed like that?
- Huh?
Are you being stylish?
Ow!
I'm going to go change.
Ouch. Hey, Ani-san! Me, too!
Seriously, what's their problem?
Okay, Iwashimizu-sensei,
I'm heading to the dressing...
Iwashimizu-sensei?
I'm going to the dressing room
to get changed.
Oh, right.
The thing is...
Master Issho forced Akane's dad
to quit Rakugo.
This year's head judge will be...
I finally understand
why she made that face.
I'm sure she's carrying a tremendous load
as she takes on this competition.
Will she be all right?
The judge today is Issho Arakawa.
And there's also one other judge
from that day.
Pardon me! Good morning!
Hey, good morning.
Is that cologne?
You're as stylish as ever, huh?
It's etiquette.
I'm no spring chicken,
so I wouldn't want to smell offensive.
Is that right?
Those things never bother me!
It bothers some people, you know.
Especially the smell of garlic, say.
Oh.
You've had ramen again, right?
You sure love that stuff, Ryujaku.
I rarely have a chance to come to Tokyo,
except for the Karaku Cup.
I can't help it!
That's our rising Kamigata Rakugo star.
Your schedule is so packed in Osaka
that you have no time to come to Tokyo.
Please, stop joking around!
Look at you, Master Ikken,
so swamped yourself.
Not just with Rakugo,
but shooting movies and TV shows.
A mainstay who supports the leader,
Issho Arakawa,
as one of the Arakawa Arch Four!
Also known as Ikken the Hedonist!
IKKEN ARAKAWA
And now you're closing in on the number
two spot in the Arakawa pecking order.
I'm not even in the same league
as an esteemed senpai like you!
You give me way too much credit.
Also, no mention of this "number two"
business in front of my master.
There'd be no laughing it off.
Man, that's scary!
I mean, I've heard all kinds of rumors,
like they won't appear together.
But are Master Issho and Master Shiguma
really on such bad terms?
Well, that's not far off the mark.
Back when the predecessor
was alive and well,
I've heard that they actually got along.
But that seems unfathomable now.
Yikes.
Still, unlike those days,
he now shows a different side of himself,
internally and externally,
so what more can you ask for?
No, no, Master Issho
is still terrifying enough!
I worry about what he might do today
as a judge.
Come on, just watch, and you'll find out.
Well, I guess right now,
I'm scared of a hot cup of tea!
Okay, thank you very much!
That was Megane Chuotei
with "Scared of Manju"!
I have to say, you really threw yourself
into that performance!
All right, let's see. Master Issho!
Any thoughts you'd like to share?
Well, that was a fine performance!
It's just a pity about the way
you used your pauses.
Put more effort into varying your pace,
and you'll do even better.
Th-Th-Thank you very much!
He's certainly being kind.
Nothing like
the way he is during training.
It pleases me to see the younger
generation rising to the challenge
of carrying on
the traditional arts so boldly.
Yeah, that reeks of trying
to curry favor with young people.
Hey! Karashi...
Huh? Didn't you think so, too?
Hm?
What's up, Little Jugemu?
Ogling me like that.
You're embarrassing me.
Huh? Little Jugemu? I'm...
Right, right.
Now here's a question for you.
What's the "shihon," or key, that you need
to be successful in life?
What's your answer?
What? Chiffon?
The answer is,
to be able to trust yourself.
In life, there's no better buff
than self-esteem.
How much can you trust yourself
when the going gets tough?
It's important to stack up evidence
that you're worthy of that trust.
See, that's what I've got.
The confidence to shut up those who go on
and on about the classics and tradition!
Thank you very much!
And now, let's turn to our next performer.
The question is this next guy.
He brought the house down both
last year and the year before, but...
- Karashi!
- We've been waiting for you!
What will Master Issho think
of his Rakugo?
I'm going to show you now.
A new kind of Rakugo!
What's my favorite thing?
Hmm, comedy skits, I guess?
Or actually...
What's my favorite thing?
Hmm, Rakugo, I guess?
That makes me sound more hardcore, right?
SEEKING NEW MEMBERS
RAKUGO CLUB
WELCOME
Hey, are you there, Old Master?
Ah, is that you, Hattsan?
Come on up and... Huh?
Are you a new recruit?
Well, something like that.
But...
What's that? You want a long nail
so you can hang a broom on it?
What are you talking about?
I'm a carpenter, you know!
You don't have to tell me how long
of a nail I need to hang a broom on!
And that's when he took out
a shingle nail that was eight sun long.
Hey, hand me that hammer.
Eight sun? That's a unit of length, right?
It just doesn't click.
Use centimeters, for crying out loud.
I mean, what exactly is a shingle nail?
If you don't get it, then it's so boring.
Which is why...
Seems like there are know-it-alls
wherever you go.
In a lab at a certain university,
a grad student is presenting
his research to his professor.
That concludes my presentation
on the environmental problems
of managing livestock.
My research is progressing
based on best-practice scheduling,
while maintaining a buffer,
and setting priorities.
I noticed this yesterday,
but this kid is telling a Rakugo story,
only it's set in modern times.
Is this allowed?
What's with that face?
Listen, you...
There are pros who also perform original
Rakugo tales with updated settings.
Rakugo isn't just about the classics.
If you're a reporter, do your homework!
S-Sorry about that.
So this is an original by this kid?
The thing is, it is and it isn't.
Huh?
Excuse me.
I've heard your presentation, but there's
probably room to rethink the BM issue.
BM? B... Uh, well...
You might be right about that.
The graduate student is too proud to admit
that he doesn't understand what BM means.
He has the other lab members
try to find out what this "BM" means.
Man, what am I gonna do? What's this "BM"?
I'm coming up empty!
Senpai! I'm coming in!
About that pork consumption report
the other day...
Right, the materials are on that shelf.
Hey. I know!
I'll use the lab students to find out.
Hey, listen.
About that BM thing
I mentioned two weeks ago...
What now?
Remember I told you to write
a summary on BM?
And go collect samples
while you were at it?
Huh? What do you mean?
You never mentioned...
Yes, I did!
- But...
- I told you, all right?
If you haven't done it yet,
get it done by this evening.
What?
Just as I thought,
it's similar to that story I heard before.
Good job noticing that.
This is "Tenshiki" updated
for modern-day audiences.
It's adapted Rakugo.
It's an adaptation?
The story settings and key wordplay
have been changed,
but the structure remains the same.
What is Senpai talking about?
I'm hearing this for the first time.
What's this BM?
Hey! Mika! Got a second?
I'm doing research on BM right now.
Oh, you are?
I happen to like it quite a lot.
You know, the TV shows, the shopping...
It's enjoyable in a different way
than broadcast TV, you know?
Also, the antenna looks so cool!
Huh? Where are you going?
You're talking about BS!
Broadcasting satellite!
He takes the structure
of classic Rakugo stories,
and updates them to modern times,
while making them resonate
with a student-centric audience.
Then pack them with scores of relatable
elements that make them laugh.
Oh, right, BM? So many of them
are visually intriguing these days, huh?
They even have some that are
"exclusively online"
or "exclusively for viewing in taxis."
And if your favorite celebrity's in one,
you can't help but buy lots!
This is, so to speak...
No, those are CMs! Commercials!
Jeez, every last one of you!
Rakugo geared specifically towards
scoring laughs at the Karaku Cup.
Hey.
Honeyama! Glad I ran into you.
The thing is, I have
an urgent research project on BM.
BM? I've got one. Want to see it?
Really? That would be awesome!
Thanks! Can you show me, please?
Huh? This is it?
Yup. My brand-new car
that my dad bought for me.
Only look, okay?
It's my policy to not let anyone
but girls ride in it. See ya.
I'm not talking about that kind of BM!
My dad bought it for me, psh!
A guy like that is more like a BM
for "boneheaded man-child"!
The Karaku Cup two years ago...
I was shocked when I saw his Rakugo
for the first time.
That was no shallow affectation
of original Rakugo.
He'd kept the laugh-inducing structure
of classic Rakugo stories intact,
and created totally new stories,
replete with outstanding wordplay.
It led to an undisputed victory.
And last year, he stood above
the rest of the students,
becoming the first-ever consecutive winner
of the Karaku Cup in history.
How else to describe him but as
a student Rakugo maverick of his time?
Excuse me, ma'am,
but what do you mean by BM?
Oh, BM? BM stands for "bowel movement."
It means to defecate or "excrement."
What? Ex-Excrement...
Meaning, um... P-Poop?
Well, you can hardly discuss
livestock management
without mentioning excrement disposal.
And that's why I can't help wonder
just how his Rakugo will register
in the eyes of Master Issho,
the preeminent Rakugoka of our time?
Are you kidding me? Huh?
So all this time,
I've been digging around for poop?
I just pestered Honeyama
to show me his BM!
Ugh, it's starting to smell!
Hey, shut up!
Wait, don't tell me Senpai
doesn't know what BM stands for?
Man, this is annoying!
Why don't I just give him
some false information?
All right, so in a rush,
he finished a false report.
Senpai?
I've brought you a summary on BM,
along with some samples.
Hey, thanks for your hard work!
Hm? Coffee?
This jar is full of Bellmarks!
Oh, right, Bellmarks!
Right, that's right!
Bellmark is involved in environmental
safety campaigns, after all.
That's my junior associate!
When I need more BMs, I'll let you know!
Sure. I'll squeeze some out right away.
- What?
- Oh, I mean I'll give them to you.
All right, Senpai, you have a good dump...
Ugh! No, I mean,
good luck summarizing that report!
The times keep changing.
So even if you keep performing
these period pieces,
they won't resonate with us.
Because he said,
"Whatever you do, don't give me manju,"
everyone in the nagaya gathered
to lay manju at his pillow.
- Excuse me.
- Huh?
Nagaya's hard to grasp, so can I change it
to "apartment" or something?
Also, manju being his favorite food is...
No, listen, "Scared of Manju"
is a classic masterpiece, so...
Ah, never mind.
I'll do it my way.
Hey, w-wait a second.
H-Hey, Karashi!
And the winner of the 18th Karaku Cup is...
Karashi Nerimaya!
For performing "Scared of Idols"!
Wow!
Winning on your first try
is beyond amazing!
Not really.
All I did was give the audience
what they wanted.
Easily takes the Karaku Cup
two years in a row.
EASILY TAKES THE KARAKU CUP
TWO YEARS IN A ROW
Huh...
What's with this Karashi Nerimaya?
It's so lame.
Huh? You shut up.
Look at you, a student champion now.
Will you forget about finding a job
and become a Rakugoka?
A professional Rakugoka?
Nope, there's no way I'd ever do that.
I mean...
Whether it's schoolwork,
or sports, or job-hunting...
Guessing what the other person wants
with pinpoint precision...
That's the fun part, right?
As long as you do that,
the results will follow naturally.
Rakugo's no different.
Actually, I'd like to discuss that BM
you mentioned yesterday.
What? Right now? We're eating.
I first became interested in environmental
issues back when I was in junior high.
And I learned that collecting BM
would lead to preserving the environment.
And so I've been collecting tons
of BM that were lying around nearby.
After all that hoarding,
I've got ten years' worth!
Ten years worth?
Yes. And now I have my family's help,
so the closets at my parents' home
are bursting.
Maybe you could take a look at them today.
Uh, no thank you!
Please, no need to be shy!
I'm not being shy!
I'm going to take them out now!
Not at the table!
Before you can call it a traditional art,
Rakugo is a performance for the masses!
It's all about how many laughs
you get, right?
Here they are!
What's this, coffee?
This jar is full of Bellmarks!
Ten years' worth of BM!
What? B... M?
Bellmar... BM?
Listen. When speaking of livestock issues,
excrement, or "bowel movements"
are what one means by BM, does it not?
Uh... Oh, right! Yes, yes, that's right!
That's why I've been using Bellmarks
to grapple with the BM issue!
No, I'm not talking about your
"grappling," but rather your "grasp."
Well, well! Thank you very much!
That was Mr. Karashi Nerimaya with "BM."
Now, that was a performance
brimming with originality!
Master Ikken, what did you think?
Well, you certainly got a lot of laughs.
Your angle and tempo were both great.
I'm thinking of doing that story
at my next performance!
Thank you very much!
Now, then, Master Issho,
your thoughts, please.
To be honest, it couldn't make me laugh.
I was most likely
not part of the demographic
that you were seeking laughs from.
As proof of that,
the one who got the most laughs
from the audience members
of your generation
was, without a doubt, you!
How to take Rakugo,
this shared asset of ours,
and create your own stories out of it.
You could say that
sparing no effort to come up
with creative ideas
is a Rakugoka's destiny.
This performance of yours today...
was quite thought-provoking,
and very entertaining.
I have high hopes for you
and your future endeavors.
How awesome is that?
Master Issho
said he's got high hopes for you!
Just shut the hell up!
Don't take his lip service at face value!
Says the guy who couldn't stop smirking!
Huh? You little pest! Back off!
Ow!
Well, you get it now, don't you?
You can't beat me
with classics that lack creativity.
I'll admit it's going to be tough.
You mean that Mr. Nerimaya was that good?
He's not really that much better
than the other students.
He's compensating for his technical
immaturity by adapting his Rakugo stories.
But she's no amateur in terms of skills,
and performs the classics in a pure way.
You could say they're polar opposites.
I never thought that man
would praise adapted Rakugo.
You'd think it was the kind of approach
that he'd abhor.
I don't like the order of this lineup.
As if it weren't enough
that the next performer...
will be doing that story.
NEXT EPISODE
EXPRESSIONIST
Akane Small Talk!
So, Little Jugemu, how was my performance?
My name's not Little Jugemu!
You saw it, right?
Rakugo's new possibilities?
They'll never be in reach so long as
you're shackled to the classics.
The classics have a lot
going for them, too!
They're just so darned hard to understand.
Like, "I found 42 ryo on Shibahama."
I mean, why not just say
"I found 100 million yen"?
Because it wouldn't seem real then!
And it wouldn't fit
in your wallet, either!
You know how they called money "legs"?
Supposedly because it would disappear,
as if it had sprouted legs.
Like, who knows what that means?
Oh, that's right.
That's why it's called "legs."
Or how many "sun," "shaku," or "ken."
Why not just say
three cm, 30 cm, or 1.8 meters?
Three... Oh, right. Yeah, yeah.
Or how about "Ushimitsudoki,"
"Oyatsudoki," or "Kuremutsu"?
Why not just say, between 2 and 2:30 AM,
2 PM, or 6 PM?
Um, is that right?
Also, it's the same Yotaro, but in
"Antique Dealer," he's unemployed,
and in "Carpenter Investigation,"
he's working as a carpenter.
In "The Brocade Robe," he's got a wife.
But in "Rokurokubi,"
he's yearning for a wife.
Doesn't make sense, does it?
Wow, you've totally done your homework
on the classics, haven't you?